Register of the Witold S. Sworakowski Papers, 1868-1977
Hoover Institution Archives
Witold S. Sworakowski Papers,
1868-1977
79040
Sworakowski, Witold S.
9 manuscript boxes, 1 slide box, 4 microfilm reels, 1 phonotape reel (4.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Statistics, writings, translations, notes, maps, and printed matter, relating to the ethnography of Upper Silesia in 1910; Polish boundary questions, 1918-1945; the Paris Peace Conference of 1919; communism in Eastern Europe after World War II; and the authorship of the 1917 abdication proclamation of Tsar Nicholas II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1868-1918; Romanov, House of; Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); Communism; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918--Peace; World War, 1914-1918--Territorial questions; Europe, Eastern; Germany; Poland; Poland--Boundaries; Silesia (Germany)--Population; Russia; Russia--History--February Revolution, 1917; Phonotapes; Slides (Photography)
Biographical Note
1903, January 16 Born, Suceuava (Bukovina), Rumania
1931-33 Member, Research Institute on Nationality Problems, Warsaw, Poland
1934 Graduated from Academy of Political Science, Warsaw, Poland
1934-36 Member, World League of Poles Abroad
1936-1945 Legation Secretay and Vice Consul with the Polish Foreign Service in Riga, Prague, Kovno, Curitiba, New York and Chicago
1947 Hoover Institution fellow
1947-1952 Research associate and curator, Hoover Institution
1952-55 Assistant professor, Stanford University
1955-1965 Associate professor, Stanford University
1955-1967 Assistant Director, Hoover Institution
1965 Author, The Communist International and Its Front Organizations
1967-1969 Associate Director, Hoover Institution
1970-79 Consultant to the Director, Hoover Institution Emeritus professor, Stanford University
1973 Author, World Communism: A Handbook
1979 Died, Stanford, California
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1960-1973. (box 1)
  Correspondence, reports, and identification card, relating to W. S. Sworakowski's career and personal life. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1939-1977. (Box 1)
  Letters, reports, memoranda, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1941-1975. (Boxes 1-6)
  Handwritten, typewritten, and printed copies of speeches and writings with related correspon-dence, notes and research materials. Arranged chronologically.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1910-1975. (boxes 6-9)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, clippings, articles, notes, maps, printed matter and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- MICROFILMS, 1868-1962. (Microfilm cabinet)
  4 microfilm reels of various Hoover Instiution library holdings and writings of W. S. Sworakowski.
- PHONOTAPE, 1972. (Tape cabinet)
  1 phonotape of an interview of Ivan Bydzan (John Bittson), conducted by W. S. Sworakowski, December 28, 1972.
- PHOTOGRAPHS. (10.A-V)
  See photo card catalogue for description.
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1960-1973
  - Curriculum vitae, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lenin State Library card, 1965 (Folder 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1939-1977
  - Association of Cieszyn Silesians in Great Britain, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ferrari, Thomas J., 1952 (Folder 4)
  - Grabianka, S., 1954 (Folder 5)
  - Heller, Ernest, 1957 (Folder 6)
  - Hoover Institution, 1968-1971 (Folder 7)
  - Kallert, Georg, 1957 (Folder 8)
  - Kemp, Arthur, 1956 (Folder 9)
  - Kwapiszewski, M., 1944 (Folder 10)
  - La Grange, 1973 (Folder 11)
  - Lewytzkyj, Boris, 1968 (Folder 12)
  - Miller, Bernice, 1957-59 (Folder 13)
  - Pilsudski Institute of America, 1949, 1977 (Folder 14)
  - Silvansky, J., 1957 (Folder 15)
  - Skirpa, K., 1954 (Folder 16)
  - Stachiewicz, General, 1939-1940 (Folder 17)
  - Zaleski, August, 1964 (Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 19)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1941-1975
  - Drafts and notes (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Chronology of British Policy," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 21)
  - "Chronology of Soviet-American Relations," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 22)
  - "Chronology of Soviet Policies," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 23)
  - "Chronology of the United Nations," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 24)
  - "Chronology of World Relations," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 25)
  - "Hans von Seeckt - the War Criminal Who Escaped Trial," n.d. Typescript with annotations. Notes and clippings included. (Folder 26)
  - "The Hoover Institution Collection on Poland," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 27)
  - "Poland and Russia in War, Revolution and Peace," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 28-29)
  - "Poland and Russia in War, Revolution and Peace," n.d. Typescript. (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - "The Poles in the Soviet Union, Facts and Figures," n.d. Printed copy. (Folder 3)
  - Review of Half a Century of Russian Serials, 1917-1968 compiled by Michael Schatoff, 1971, n.d. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 4)
  - Review of Historia Polakow na Bukowinie by Emil Biedrzycki, 1973, n.d. Typescript (photocopy). (Folder 5)
  - "Russia, 1918-1920 - Intervention," n.d. Typescript and bibliographies. (Folder 6)
  - "Russia's Nationality Problems," n.d. Typewritten and handwritten drafts. (Folder 7)
  - Untitled fragments and writings
    - Communism (Folder 8)
    - Communist International (Folder 9-10)
    - Poland - History- 1917-1926 (Folder 11)
    - Poland - History- 1917-1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Russian political parties, 1918 (Folder 2)
    - Solzhenitzyn, Aleksandr (Folder 3)
    - Soviet Central Asia (Folder 4)
    - U.S. foreign policy, 1937-1948 (Folder 5)
  - "Notatka dla Pana Ministra Stronskiego w Sprawie Przyszlej Granicy na Gornym Slasku," 1941. Typescript with annotations. (Folder 6)
  - "Sprawa Gornego Slaska na Konferencji Pokojwej w Paryzu, 1919-1921r.," January 1941. Typescript (carbon copy). Five maps included. (Folder 7)
  - Review of "Upper Silesia Past and Present" (Polish Fortnightly Review (London), October 1, 1941), February 10, 1941. Typescript. Issue of Polish Fortnightly Review included. (Folder 8)
  - "Poland's Eastern Frontiers From the Paris Peace Conference at Paris to the Conference at Yalta - Facts and Documents," 1945. Typescript with notes. In English and Polish. (Folder 9-10)
  - "Working Memorandum on the Problem of the Soviet Orbit," April 28, 1948. A study guide for the Brookings Institution. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 11)
  - Memo on Polish-Soviet relations, May 1948. Typescript with annotations. (Folder 12)
  - "France in the World Community," outline of project, 1949. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 13)
  - "Poland in the World Community," outlines of project, 1949. Typewritten and mimeographed copies. (Folder 14)
  - "The Soviet Union in the World Community," outline of project, 1949. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 15)
  - "Observations on the 'Working Memorandum on the Problem of the Soviet Orbit,'" March 15, 1949. Typescript. (Folder 16)
  - "Notes on the German Collection of Polish Documents Concerning the Outbreak of the War in 1939," August 16, 1949. Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "List of Archive Material Dealing With Federation Plans for Central and Eastern Europe Developed During the Second World War," December 1954. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 2)
  - "Eastern European Images of Russia in the Nineteenth Century: The Polish-Czech View," paper presented at the Far Western Slavic Conference, Los Angeles, April 23-24, 1960. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 3)
  - "The Red Myth," television series produced by KQED, San Francisco, 1962
    - Correspondence relating to, 1960-65 (Folder 4-5)
    - Drafts of selected scripts. Typescripts with annotations. (Folder 6)
  - The Communist International and Its Front Organizations, Stanford, 1965. Review of book, in German, and letter to reviewer. (Folder 7)
  - "Polish Archives in the Hoover Institution," ca. 1969. Typescript (photocopy). (Folder 8)
  - "Poland's Baltic Policy, 1918-1920," speech, Stanford, November 20, 1970. Typescript. (Folder 9)
  - "The Authorship of the Abdication Document of Nicholas II," 1971. Typescript with annotations and and reprint from The Russian Review, July 1971. Included is related correspondence and research notes. (Folder 10-11)
  - World Communism: A Handbook, Hoover Institution Press, 1973.
    - Correspondence relating to (Folder 12-13)
    - Drafts and notes (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
    - Drafts and notes (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
    - List of contributors (Folder 6)
  - "Herbert Hoover, America's Food Administrator, 1917-19," paper presented at the Hoover Centennial Seminar, West Branch, Iowa, February 13, 1974. Typescript. (Folder 7)
  - "Note on Hoover Seminars," West Branch, Iowa, February 13-15, 1974. Typescript. (Folder 8)
  - "Note Concerning Slownik Geograficzny Krolestwa Polskiego i Innych Ziem Slowianskich, 1880-1914," March 26, 1974. Typescript (photocopy). (Folder 9)
  - Interview on the history of the Hoover Institution, November 1975. Typescript (photocopy). (Folder 10)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1910-1975
  - Brest-Litovsk Peace Conference, 1917-18, meetings of political commissions. In Russian. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Brzezinski, Zbigniew, "The Hostile Fantasy World of Zbigniew Brzezinski," by Lyndon La Rouche, U.S. Labor Party, New York, 1972 (Folder 12)
  - Communism
    - General (Folder 13)
    - Stanford Studies of the Communist System, June 1945 (Folder 14)
    - Szawlowski, Richard, "The System of the International Organizations of the Communist Countries," n.d. (Folder 15)
  - Europe, foreign policy. Brzezinski, Zbigniew, "Peaceful Engagement in Europe's Future," Columbia University, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - International Workers Organization (Miedzynarodowy Zwiazek Robotniczy), Polish Section, 1932-1946 (Folder 2)
  - Kosciuszko Squadron (Folder 3)
  - Kwiatkowski family genealogy (Folder 4)
  - League of Nations, application of the Ukrainian Republic for admission, November 1920 (Folder 5)
  - Lithuania, foreign policy. Grinius, Colonel K., "Miejsce Niepodleglej Litwy w Przyszlej Europie i w Systemie Pokoju Swiatowego," September 2, 1943. (Folder 6)
  - Paris Peace Conference, 1919
    - Commission on Polish Affairs (Folder 7)
    - Territorial questions (Folder 8-9)
  - Poland
    - Archives and libraries, ca. 1920s (Folder 10)
    - Border with Czechoslovakia, 1938, maps (Folder 11)
    - Boundaries, 1917-19 (Folder 12)
    - Boundaries, 1917-19 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Foreign relations
      - Czechoslovakia
        - September-November 1938 (Folder 2)
        - Cieszyn, 1942 (Folder 3)
      - Great Britain (Folder 4)
      - Lithuania (Folder 5)
    - History, World War II
      - Cultural losses (Folder 6)
      - German occupation, 1939-1945, Na Tropach Smetka (Folder 7)
      - "Polska-Niemcy-Rosja," by Ks. Stanislaw Orlemanski, ca. 1943 (Folder 8)
    - Social conditions, 1932 (Folder 9)
  - Poles in foreign countries, 1950 (Folder 10)
  - Poles in Siberia (Folder 11)
  - Poles in the U.S.
    - General (Folder 12)
    - Alfred Jurzykowski Foundation, "Jurzykowski Millenium Awards, 1963-66," New York (Folder 13)
    - Bolek, Franciszek, "Ruch Umyslowy wsrod Polonji Amery- kanskiej," 1943 (Folder 14)
  - Polish-Soviet War, 1921 (Folder 15)
  - Russian revolutionary pamphlets, decrees, orders, and proclamations of the Provisional Workers and Peasants Government of the Russian Republic, October 25 -December 1, 1917 (Folder 16)
  - Silesia, Upper
    - Ethnic composition, 1910, population study and statistical data (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - "Regulations for the Plebiscite in Upper Silesia," December 30, 1920. Issued by the Inter-Allied Plebiscite Commission. In German and Polish. (Folder 5)
  - Soviet Union
    - Foreign relations - U.S., 20th century (Folder 6)
    - History - German occupation - German Army map of Odessa, dated December 1940 (Folder 7)
    - Politics and government - Brzezinski, Zbigniew, "Soviet Politics From the Future to the Past?" Columbia University, New York, March 1975 (Folder 8)
  - Ukraine (Folder 9)
  - United Nations Conference, San Francisco, 1945. Coded telegrams, April-May. In Polish. (Folder 10)
  - United States of America, social conditions, Brzezinski, Zbigniew, "America in the Technetronic Age," Columbia University, New York, 1967 (Folder 11)
  - World War II, underground movements, France (Folder 12)
  - Miscellany (Folder 13)
- MICROFILMS, 1868-1962
  - Reel No. 1 - Typewritten manuscript of The Communist International and Its Front Ogranizations: A Checklist of Holdings in the Library of the Hoover Institution, Part II, compiled by W. S. Sworakowski, Stanford, January 1962 (Oversize Microfilm Cabinet)
  - Reel No. 2-7 pages from Niepodleglosc (Paris), No. 81, 1868
  - Reel No. 3 - Polish historical sources from Government Documents at the Hoover Institution Library
    - Seijm Wilenski, 1922
    - Dziennik Uzredowy
    - Wybory do Sejmu w Wilnie
  - Reel No. 4 - Russian newspapers from the Hoover Institution Library
    - Izvestia (Moscow), April-May 1918
    - Novaia Zhizn' (Moscow), May-July 1918
- PHONOTAPE, 1972.
  - 1 phonotape of an interview of Ivan Bydzan (John Bittson), conducted by W. S. Sworakowski, December 28, 1972 (Oversize Tape cabinet)
- PHOTOGRAPHS.
  - See photo card catalogue for description. (Folder 10.A-V)